software engineering radio episode 49
dynamic languages for statically typed
minds
welcome listeners this is another
episode of software engineering radio in
this episode we are talking to Nicholas
Nielsen about dynamic languages for
people who have a background in more
aesthetic languages such as Java we've
recorded this episode at the Uppsala
conference in I think end of October
2006 in Portland Oregon the quality of
this recording is not that great the
reason is that I forgot to recharge the
batteries of my recording device so we
had to record it directly on the
notebook and that meant and we only have
one microphone and that means that we
have to pass around the microphone
between interviewer and interviewee
that's why you can hear these microphone
rumbles from time to time still I think
the quality is absolutely acceptable and
the content is interesting enough to not
throw it away just because of the
recording quality so Nicolas welcome to
the show thank you very much and maybe
we start by you introducing yourself a
little bit your background and then
we'll tell them to the topic my name is
Nicolas I'm consulting doing education
coaching stuff and on the west coast of
Sweden
my background is from the beginning in
better systems doing a lot of automation
automotive stuff and telematics stuff
where telecom industry meets the vehicle
industry and says the west coast of
Sweden is kind of like Detroit's in
Sweden we have a lot of vehicle industry
so even though we tend to turn up on the
server side more and more it's still
legal industry ok so let's look at the
topic if we talk about dynamic language
is what are some of the typical
languages that come to your mind and
which one is going to be the language
we're going to talk about mostly in this
presentation or in this episode and
dynamic language that I've that I did
some real work in it was a Python and
before that I mean still people and
including me were doing a lot of
JavaScript which of course in the
dynamic language but turned out to be
much much much harder since all the
browsers did not follow standards very
well
but in 2002 here at actually I had a
really good experience attending Dave
Thomas Nandi hunts Ruby need a tutorial
so we probably gonna talk most about
Ruby today and other languages that I
think will be very interesting to follow
is groovy some people say that groove is
dead before it's born more or less well
I'm not sure I mean since that I'm a
dynamic language backed by Sun I think
that may be a good thing okay then just
another remark how this episode ties in
with some of the other episodes we
already have and we will have so we
talked about Ruby in previous episodes
more on a general note and and and and
this episode will focus on some of the
programming language features that
you'll typically find in dynamic
languages such as Ruby and then in a
subsequent episode we'll talk about
domain-specific languages implemented in
Ruby with using using some of these
features we're going to talk about today
so this ties in nicely into some of the
other episodes we've already had and we
will have so some of the more
interesting or advanced features what
are what are the the key features there
I think the first thing that you notice
is the blocks which is the possibility
to pass around code to two other methods
in Java you can use the anonymous inner
classes and stuff to do things like that
but it's it's much more awkward and the
syntax really doesn't look as nice at
all
the other thing is that it really is
different I'm coming from the Java
perspective is that nothing is ever
closed you can open up a class anytime
you can mess around with it you can add
stuff you can remove stuff things that
people do in Java and have to do in Java
by byte code we being surgically going
in adding stuff which BCE LCG Lib and
all these things are doing it's not that
people can't do it in Java just as
really really hard if you have a lot
dynamic language that's no problem you
just do it it's it doesn't look any
different than in
at all and that's the main and largest
difference to me
the metaprogramming stuff and that
everything is always open that's what
people think from a static point of view
is really really dangerous so maybe
let's start with one feature that is the
typing itself how do you what is the
difference between dynamic typing and
static typing in and what is stack
typing the first thing that you see is
that you don't have to specify types
that you don't specify what type your
references are but that's just that's
just the surface let's say you have a
number 100 million or something like
that
and that's a that's a fixed number in
Ruby which is like an integer in in Java
let's say you multiply that by itself in
Java that would just wrap and there will
be some really strange number that isn't
it's not just not correct it will wrap
several times of course but in Ruby it
will realize that hmm this is too large
let's make this a larger type let's make
this a big number and something that we
actually found out just that I didn't
think Ruby did but it's something that
you found out during the Union tutorial
that was if you divide it again it will
actually turn it down to fix num again
so it's not just that you don't have to
specify the type it's also that an
object can dynamically change its type
at runtime yes exactly and that's that's
what it's doing and that's if if the
environment realize that this type is
not longer sufficient it will change and
just to make this clear to our listeners
this is not the same as like
polymorphism in Java in Java what you
can of course do you can have a
reference that is typed statically to
some class and then you can
polymorphically let it point to
subclasses of that class but you can
never take a given object and change the
dynamic type it's real class at runtime
you can always cast it but that's just
changing the reference time it's not
changing the objects nature itself
exactly that's if you look at some of
the classic object-oriented examples
when you have something some object they
want to change role stuff like that
that's really hard because then you
really have to change
you really have to change type and
that's that's harder in that language so
that means also that if you do this then
you probably I mean as we all know you
don't have any compiler checks whether
types are compatible and you probably
also don't have a compiler check that
checks whether if you invoke a method on
some object whether the respective class
has this method and that opens some
interesting possibilities with regards
to the method not found or what is it
called in Ruby so can you talk about
this a little bit and maybe yeah
so what does some of some of the tricks
you can do with that I think that's
where people think is the the largest
drawback too because since it's really
really hard to figure out all the type
is it's really really hard to figure out
what methods are on the object you're
currently working on for your tool which
means that the intellisense code
completion stuff is is gone it's really
really hard to make a tool that helps at
that said and when you when you talk to
the object you don't talk about
interfaces in a normal sense
you speak about the question is not are
you of this type the question is can you
respond to the messages I will send you
which is which equals to to the methods
I will call will you respond to those
can you do anything with with those on
the highest point you can ask an object
what methods what messages it can
respond to but you usually don't not too
often at least it's you just send the
message in a static language it will
start out by looking in the V table and
you and the caller will decide if the
coulee the one who accepts the message
should accept message if it can do it so
the caller or on the compiler next
choice in dynamic language you will just
send a message to the object and you
will see what happens usually it will
answer since it's you usually don't pass
around run the wrong objects but it may
be so that it doesn't have that method
then the object itself can it will get
an it will get the message that oh here
is a message and you don't you can't
respond to it she will end up in a
special
that called method missing method
missing takes a few arguments one is the
name of the method and then it gets the
arguments in the end which makes it
possible to parse the method name which
makes for instance the trick that you
can do finder methods find by name and
address even though there is no find by
name and address method but if the
object has the proper properties it can
decide for itself that yes I can
construct some clever answer from the
question I just got and doesn't have to
can't even be checked in compiling so we
already mentioned before that there is
this feature of code blocks so probably
most people know the command pattern
from from java programming or something
so can you elaborate what what a block
is and and also what closures are and we
talked about that before the before the
recording here and and maybe elaborate
on on some of the differences or what
you think the differences are and some
of the conflicts or discussions around
that I think this is an interesting
topic because most people probably don't
know the difference and if we don't know
it either no problem
but let's elaborate on that a little bit
what is a block what is a closure a
block in Ruby is it's just a block of
code that it's the reference
it's not the reference but today you
have you put it in in in two curly
braces or between two end it's a block
of code that you can send it to other to
other methods usually when you call a
library some some library method it it
can take a block of code that it will
execute it's it's callback mechanism to
illustrate that if you have an array of
elements and you want to multiply all
the elements by two instead of writing
an explicit loop and then doing the
multiplication yourself you just tell
the array to iterate and pass in the
behavior that it should kind of apply to
all the elements so you write a piece of
code block that has a basically that
says multiply the argument to the block
by two and then you tell the array to
apply it to all of its elements so you
passed in a piece of behavior as an
object itself right exact
and if if you look at Java for instance
the I think the most common example is a
comparison when you do sorting and stuff
like that you have to pass in little
floss instead of just a little method or
a little code block that will say which
object is larger than the alot object
from this specific perspective block
it's probably the only thing in Ruby
that's not an object except when you
want it to be because then it will turn
into something that Ruby calls a proc it
will it binds to the local variables and
you can pass it around as an object with
there's actually no difference from any
other objects in that sense and that's
supposed to me what closures were code
block bound to local variables that you
actually can't pass around but I got
some really really interesting questions
on the tutorial so I realized that I
probably don't know that's probably even
more difference is that that's a so far
lost on me but I'm gonna find Eric Maya
later and I'm gonna ask him what the
difference really is because he said at
the speaker job that he he really hopes
that Ruby will get closures right in the
next release and I'm gonna ask what he
really meant yeah that's the the
discussions between language geeks so
yep to get back to this bound to local
variables that means that if you define
a block at some point and during the
definition of this block you reference
variables in the environment of that
block then if you pass the block around
or make it into a project and execute it
later the environment is the the
environment of the time when you define
the block so it kind of remembers the
environment from the place of its
definition right because I think that is
a very cool thing precisely and that's
and that's what the functional languages
has done all the time because that makes
it rather easy to create a function that
creates functions you can have you can
create function that has some variable
points and then you can pass in
arguments to that function and it you'll
get another function that is that has
those variables that it remembers
and really you create functions that
creates other functions you write code
that write code so as far as I remember
isn't that called carrying or something
yeah that's what they call carrying in
function languages so that means if you
have for example a function that takes
two arguments X and Y and for example
takes X to the to the yth power to the
power of Y it's probably the correct
term then you can bind Y for example to
two and create a function that only
takes one parameter X and basically it
takes two to the power of two and take
that as a separate function so you
partially bind the values right yes but
yeah exactly what they do and it's a I
think it's a rather rather nice thing
and as far as I know there's only that's
only possible in functional languages
and some of the dynamic languages yeah I
know it from Lisp and and I think it's
possible in small tone I don't think
anyway I'm not an expert there okay so
that that was blocks and closures that's
Ruby also have continuations Ruby
doesn't have continuations right now but
if the rumors are correct they will be
completely removed in Ruby 2 then we'll
just be gone so they're they're removing
continuations so maybe baby can you
please briefly explain what a
continuation it is before we discuss
about whether it's there whether it's
going to be removed continuations is one
of the things that I tend to think is
the hardest thing to get my head around
because it's kind of like time machines
like having separate stacks and stuff
and then you go back and forth in time
teamwork
made a really really nice illustration
of continuation at rubyconf last year
but he used Selda when he and he used I
don't know the the character's name is
Zelda but he was first it was 11 years
old and then he went to the magic stone
and he turned 18 and then run around was
18 for a while and then he came back he
did stuff and then he came back and he
was 11 again and continued where were
you when I left off so continuations is
that the only killed feature
there are not many uses that seem to be
very widespread it seems to be the
continuation frameworks for for web
applications seaside is the the only
really well used example I've ever heard
of continuations there's also rife I
think in the Java world but it's still
kind of a niche thing yeah that's true
that's true this this mechanism
obviously makes a lot of trouble for
language makers so Matt's just said I'm
gonna take it out in Ruby too because it
makes it makes more stuff hard than then
they use actually it's boring so I'm
trying to give an example I might be
wrong here and we might cut this out if
I'm talking complete nonsense if you
have something that creates a sequence
of numbers okay a sequence generator
then what you can do with continuations
is you can basically implement that the
generator in a way that says basically a
for loop counting phone from one run to
five million and then you basically tell
the so and the body of the follow would
be a statement that many people call
yield and that basically says return the
current value yield the number the
current number of the of the iterator
like yield I if you iterate over the
variable I so you would grill the yield
I that means somebody who calls this
function give me the next value would
get this return value like five in the
sequence and then the the continuation
kind of remembers that it's currently at
this place it's like a temporary return
and if you call this function again it
continues from there counts one up and
returns the next value so that's the the
kind of canonical example that I know
for for continuations and yeah sounds
like a nice feature but I haven't it's
not in many languages as we all know
nothing I think you're I think you're
right but it's hard to think in in
temporal and temporal times in that way
and that's I think that's probably the
main reason why it's it's not used that
much okay let's let's get into more
solid ground open classes what is that
let's say you have a class let's say you
would like to for instance in the Java
world you would like to add an aspect
you would like to add an off
or before aspect to do that you have to
use special tools that the bytecode
weaving and stuff if you would do that
in dynamic language you will just open
up the clause and Ruby will just just
type class and the class name again and
then you will redefine the method if you
want to keep the old method you just
alias it and give it a new name
but you hopefully remember that and then
write your what's the new method that's
gonna do stuff before or after and then
it may or may not call that the old
method depending on if it's his
gardening stuff or if it's just doing
some logging stuff before so just you
can open up clauses you can add stuff to
it you can you can add method you can
remove methods you can take out member
variables you can you can actually say
in runtime that oh I'd like to I'd like
to extend this clause in rather so if it
implemented in Java without tools like
aspectj what you do is probably you'd
extend from the class and override the
respective method do some stuff and then
call the super method but the difference
is of course that this creates a new
class a different one and if people want
to use objects they have to make sure
they're actually instantiating this new
type so in Ruby what you can then do is
you can basically you can spread the
definition of a class over several
artifacts so you can open up a class
means you just add or remove to an
existing class right yeah exactly that's
exactly how it works and since
everything is interpreted it whenever it
encountered that this new definition it
will just start using it from from that
point so that also answers another
question that I wanted to talk about and
that is the importance of aspect
oriented programming in dynamic
languages as some of you might know the
history of aspectj
and AOP is that it has historically come
from meta object protocols so one could
argue that that aspect oriented
programming is kind of the stuff you've
always done in dynamic language is
hacked in a way so that is applicable to
static languages so so am i right in
thinking that AOP isn't such big
passwords in the dynamic language
community yes you you can't you don't
hear that discussion much at all there's
actually an aspect our and it's a guy in
Gothenburg whom I just met he's actually
been involved in that so it's gonna be
really interesting to speak to him about
this but since since you do most or even
all of the tricks with the standard
language features there's not much of a
discussion actually so it's just part of
the of the language and not a big a big
deal another thing that I would guess is
that testing is probably even more
important than in static language is
because the compiler doesn't do you know
type checking so you'd have to do a lot
more testing is that correct no since
you're supposed to do that testing
anyway so you're not supposed to do more
testing you had you you were supposed to
do it anyway because if you just if you
just think that the compiler will save
you then then you will be in trouble
anyway okay let's put it that way you
rely more on the fact that you have more
tests because the compiler I mean there
are obviously some errors the compiler
catches so it doesn't do it in dynamic
languages so test-driven development is
okay it's not more important but it's
it's critical that you have sufficient
coverage yeah that's true yeah I'm just
kidding
but still yes the tests help but that's
also that takes when I first when I
first started out with dynamic languages
when you started playing with JavaScript
I think the the most the biggest pain
was the it was really hard to test this
was in the browser you you had problems
finding those stuff by the compiler
actually helped you with when I in kind
of path in Ruby for five years ago then
I was already test driven so I didn't I
didn't have a problem anymore the
problem just went away but it took a
while before I realized that it went
away because of the tests because the
tests don't only check that I am working
with the correct types it's also
checking all the other stuff of course
that actually using the right values and
things that the compiler can never ever
do this brings us to the to the next
point which is I mean we named this app
is
basically in a way that suggests that we
kind of want to convince static language
users to at least take a serious look at
dynamic languages so what do you think
is the best process the best you know
set of steps or whatever to go from
static programming to dynamic
programming from what you just said I
take that it's a good idea to to for
example get used to test-driven
development because that's something
that'll help you use dynamic languages
are there other things that you'd
recommend you know like a team lead to
do in order to convince a team that
dynamic languages are great so what's
the process of going from static to
dynamic I think first of all like you
said test test tests are important but
also since with like within new
technologies you should just start doing
a mission-critical project and this way
what we started out doing was creating
tools because you always had tools and
you have you have your build chains that
do this and that and they usually do
have to write some some special code and
writing and tasks in Java is actually
not that fun
try using stuff like JRuby and things I
got to just try to sneak it in if you
want to try to do what I appreciate more
and more is these small applications
that normally took a couple days to do
when you get a little bit fluent in in
dynamic languages and if you find some
some some frameworks that can help you
there are they're people starting
discussing and throw away throw away
software software that you're right
that's gonna you're gonna use for for a
week or so and then you gonna throw it
away and you usually usually do suffer
that by hand instead you don't you don't
write a program to do it because it's
the investment is too high but let's say
that investment is much lower start out
playing with dynamic language to do do
stuff like that that really can do small
incremental stuff for you and then when
you get more confident try to use if you
let's say you're in the dot environment
play with ironpython Python this is
dotnet IO Python works internet and
dotnet is meant to be
seven languages use c-sharp for the poor
for some stuff you use ironpython other
stuff use this basic visual basic where
it where it's the most elegant solution
try to be more pragmatic and use more
than one language instead of saying we
are a Java shop we are donut shop
so how far along are those
implementations of dynamic languages on
the mainstream platform speed Java
or.net I am Python is released in at
least version 1.0 I think there may be
an upgrade to that and I mean it's
backed by Microsoft and the creator
works for Microsoft nowadays it's also
the same guy who wrote Jade on JRuby is
coming along it's a I think it's in
version 0.8 0.9 something like that
I think it's 0.9 and son just hired the
two main developers so JRuby has
compared to C Ruby
some really interesting features and
it's that it actually uses Java Java
real threads Java native threads which
makes threading in JRuby possibly even
better than in Syria because that's one
of the weakest spots and still there's
some features that are lacking that
Syria we can do but there it's it's
really coming close just an editorial
note this session is recorded that
upsala 2006 in October end of October in
2006 in Portland Oregon so by the time
you'll hear this on the podcast a
statement like son has just hired people
might not be completely in time so so
just as a remark so if we look at JRuby
do you know whether it's actually an
interpreter of Ruby implement in Java or
is it that Ruby is basically compiled
down to bytecode so is it the native
implementation of Ruby on the VM or is
it just writing the interpreter in you
know as it happens Java as far as I
understood it's a complete rewrite it's
a rewritten from the from the ground up
this there's nothing nothing left so
that so the point is that okay so that
means that you can probably integrate
you can
use Java classes from within a ruby
program a JRuby program and the other
way around
exactly and then they there they can
speak to to enterprise javabeans and
there are examples of calling all sorts
of strange Java stuff and I think they
even got Ruby on Rails working on the
JVM okay and and I think the question I
asked before about whether it's an
interpreter in Java or whether it's
using native Java features is probably I
should have thought before about before
I asked the question because all those
meta programming features which we'll
talk about in a subsequent episode with
Obie Fernandes you can't do that in the
Java you can't and runtime modifier
classes easily so that's probably the
reason why it's in quotes just a ruby
interpreter written in Java running on
the VM yes just yeah it said in quotes
so and and on the.net platform I've
always heard these these talks about the
dotnet platform being better suited for
implementing multiple languages compared
to the JVM because JVM the JVM has
always been or has been implemented with
the idea of running Java which is a
statically typed object-oriented
language and rumors have it that the
dotnet VM CLR is implemented in a way
that it for example supports functional
languages natively there is always this
example that it supports tail recursion
natively so is ironpython implemented as
a native CL our language or is it a
titan interpreter written in C sharp or
whatever I have no clue at all actually
not at all and but the rumor when
speaking of what you said that the rumor
is that the sealord's better is I don't
know how true this is but the creator of
Jonathan when it was about - it was
about to write paper about how bad the
CLR was for dynamic languages but he he
thought that he should try first so he
started playing with it and realized
that it was probably much better than
JVM and well now he's hired by Microsoft
and son is playing catch-up and adding
adding more and more stuff to JVM - to
make it easier to do that with language
so should people use JRuby or groovy
that depends a lot of what you wanna do
the the problem I have when coming to
JRuby and pythons iPhone and ironpython
stuff like that is that you have two
libraries you have the the native like
the the normal libraries for Python or
Ruby and then you encounter the dotnet
or the Java library and it's like the
old thing when you program C++ in in
Microsoft MFC environments the stuff
should use the Microsoft string so
should use the the you know use the
standard C Papa strings or and how do i
do all the conversion stuff you're back
there again when you when you run a
language on on such a rich library so
you're saying the real issue is today
for people to learn platforms and and
frameworks and not languages so the
language is ultimately not that
important I think languages are really
important actually
but like the the problem with switching
languages is you have to you have to
rethink some concepts and that's hard
that's that's the the main the main aha
things but when you're done that then
you still have six months of learning
libraries before you you really feel
that you are even close to productive so
that's that's the that's a hurdle that I
really would try to figure out a good
way to get around ok so I think this
wraps it up more or less so anything
else you want to say is like some some
some pearls of wisdom that you'd like to
leave with our listeners no I'm sorry I
have no posted wisdom at all but and
there are a lot of things in these
language that I like and the meta
programming stuff is really really
interesting and I really look forward to
listening to the podcast with the Adobe
about the dsls and the meta programming
stuff because I heard that it's done
some really interesting detail stuff and
I really hope people just instead of
being so afraid and saying that oh this
is this seems dangerous I think a lot of
the discussion really not a lot of
discussion but some of the comments that
we had on the tutorial was specifically
about the duck typing that you don't
know who you're calling and how do you
know that the the ones the to respond to
this message really can respond to this
message
I feel that these are exactly the same
arguments that we had for polymorphism
10-15 years ago so
let's not let's just not keep repeating
the same arguments have a good time we
have a new cool technology just play
with it to see if it's really really
that horrible thanks Nikolas for being
on the show
thank you very much as fun bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website
so other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Cowley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineer a do
website for details